Finding Aid for League of Women Voters of Berrien and Cass Counties records, 1957-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
League of Women Voters of Berrien and Cass Counties records
1957-2010
League of Women Voters of Berrien and Cass Counties.
2008024 Bm 2
The League of Women Voters of Berrien and Cass Counties is a grass roots, non-partisan political organization based in southwest Michigan. Records include newsletters, annual reports, clippings files, and scrapbooks.
3 linear feet
6 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by the organization (donor no. 9915 ) in 2007 and 2011.
Additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The League of Women Voters of Berrien and Cass Counties is a grass roots, non-partisan political organization which seeks to encourage informed and active participation in government, works to increase understanding of major public policy issues, and influences public policy through citizen education and advocacy. The organization sponsors candidate forums and registers voters. In addition, the league lobbies elected officials and works with other organizations to press its agenda at the local, state and national levels.
The League of Women Voters of Niles was founded in 1957 and has been continuously active for over fifty years. The league changed its name to the League of Women Voters of the Niles-Buchanan Area in 1971 and became the League of Women Voters of Berrien and Cass Counties in 1984.
Issues which the league has taken positions on include, but certainly are not limited to, the preservation of the Galien River Watershed, President Bush's No Child Left Behind Act, recycling, solar energy, and the environmental impact of livestock confinement on area water quality.
The League of Women Voters of Berrien and Cass Counties records document the activities of a grass roots political organization in southwest Michigan.
Subjects:
Berrien County (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Cass County (Mich.)--Politics and government.; League of Women Voters of Berrien and Cass Counties.; Women--Michigan--Berrien County--Societies and clubs.; Women--Michigan--Cass County--Societies and clubs.
- Organizational
  The Organizational files series contains a fairly complete run of newsletters and annual reports. Also extant are position papers, newspaper clippings, flyers, press releases, a small number of membership lists, and other ephemera.
  - Annual Reports, 1957-2010; 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports, Local League to Parent Organization, 1959-1977; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Berrien County Federation of Woman's Clubs, 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors, 1957-1988 (Box 1)
  - Board notebook (various materials), 2005 (Box 1)
  - President George W. Bush Visit to Niles High School, 2004 (Box 1)
  - Environmental
    - Agriculture -- animal waste -- pollution issues, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, including Galien River Watershed (Box 1)
  - Finance drive mailings, 1960s-200s (Box 1)
  - Flyers, Press Releases, and Pamphlets (Box 1)
  - Lake Michigan Inter-League Group (Betty Oostenbrug file), 1997 (Box 1)
  - Leaders Resource Kit, 2001 (Box 1)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2002-2006 (Box 1)
  - Membership Lists, 1961; 1975 undated (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, 1957-1978; 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, 1979-2010; 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - 1974-1987 (Box 2)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - Niles Clean-Up and Recycling Week (incl. wooden nickel), 1972 (Box 2)
  - Past-Presidents Club Meeting, Membership List, and Speech, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Position Papers
    - County Home Rule, 1966 (Box 2)
    - 1994-2004 (Box 2)
  - Secretary (Charlotte Omohundro) records, 2004-2005 (Box 2)
  - Secretary records (minutes and programs), 2005-2006 (Box 2)
- Topical file (Susan Gilbert presidency), 2005-2010
  This series of subject files, mainly from the period when Susan Gilbert was president of the League, is of value for the organization's position on such issues as health care reform and the proposed privatization of Social Security.
  - Board materials, 1998-2004 (Box 3)
  - Board materials (minutes of board and of annual meeting), 2004-2007 (Box 3)
  - Candidate Forum (procedures and tips), 2005 (Box 3)
  - Candidate Forum, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Candidate Forum, October 2007 (Box 3)
  - Civil rights / civil liberties, 2004 (Box 3)
  - Fund raising and membership material, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Health care legislation, 2004-2006; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Health care public forum and related, 2005-2006; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Health care, 2007; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - President's record book / album, undated; 2003-2010; 10 folders (Box 3)
  - Program planning handout, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Social Security reform (privatization), 2005 (Box 3)
  - Social Service Committee papers, 2004-2005 (Box 3)
  - State Convention, 2005 (Box 3)
    (regarding environmental issues)
  - Sunshine legislation and related, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Voter Service, 2004 (Box 3)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series contains letters from the 1960's which include state and federal Congressional communications. There is also a collection of recent correspondence dating from 2003-2006 and two topical files: the league's sponsorship of students to attend "Close Up" in Washington D.C. and the organization's name changes during the 1970's.
  - (include correspondence with members of Congress), 1960-1969 (Box 3)
  - 2003-2006 (Box 3)
  - Close Up Sponsorship, Washington, D.C. (Box 3)
  - Name Change, 1971-1976 (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series contains photographs spanning the years 2000 and 2004. Earlier photographs can be found in the scrapbooks series.
  - Gast Luncheon, Jelinek-Lasata Luncheon, Assorted, 2000 (Box 3)
  - 2000-2003 (Box 3)
  - Annual Meeting, May 2000 (Box 3)
  - State Convention, Mackinac Is, May 2003 (Box 3)
  - October 2004 (Box 3)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbooks series, six oversize volumes, provide a record of the League's activities by way of newspaper clippings, spanning 1957 through 1982 and 2000 through 2002. The scrapbooks also contain photographs, illustrations, and other ephemera.
  - 1957-1968 (Volume 1)
  - 1968-1970 (Volume 2)
  - 1970-1976 (Volume 3)
  - 1977-1982 (Volume 4)
  - Sun Day / Solar Power Fair, 1978 (Volume 5)
  - 2000-2002 (Volume 6)